const e=JSON.parse('[{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a facilitative message?","options":{"A":"‘Run on’ question","B":"Self-disclosure","C":"‘I want’ message","D":"Silence","E":"Interpretation"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Questions used in clinical interviews can be either facilitative or obstructive. Facilitative messages help the interview to flow, establish a rapport and gain the confidence of the patient. For example, open-ended questions, facilitating statements, reflections, silence, interpretations, positive reinforcements, etc. Run on or polythematic questioning refers to the process of asking the patient a number of questions at the same time. For example, ‘Have you felt high in spirits, gone on spending sprees and made foolish investments in the past week?’ These questions can be obstructive. Self disclosures are statements about oneself (the psychiatrist) that may help establish a rapport with the patient. I want messages are generally used when the interview fails to progress because the patient is stuck on the same topic. In this case, the psychiatrist could say politely that he or she wants to move on to other topics."},{"question":"A psychiatrist at an early stage of his initial assessment interview asks the patient, ‘Can you tell me about your depression?’ Which of the following interview techniques is he utilizing?","options":{"A":"Closed-ended questions","B":"Open-ended questions","C":"Reflecting","D":"Facilitation","E":"Put down question"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Open-ended questions reflect a topic that the psychiatrist may want to explore, but leaves it open to the patient to say what he/she thinks is important. These questions are used to start the interview and, later on, can lead to specific closed-ended questions. Put down questions are where the underlying message is a criticism. For example ‘How can you complain when you have got an A grade in your GCSE?’ Facilitation statements encourage the patient to continue along a particular line of thought. For example, statements such as ‘Go on’; ‘Proceed’; ‘What else’ are facilitation statements."},{"question":"Which of the following is an open-ended question?","options":{"A":"Tell me about yourself?","B":"Could you tell me the name of the prime minister?","C":"It seems as if you feel people are against you?","D":"What do you find stressful in your job?","E":"Do you have trouble falling asleep?"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"A question whose answer cannot be a simple yes or no, or a single factual answer that can be classified as right or wrong, is an open-ended question, such as the question given in 3. A. (See also Question 2)."},{"question":"During a clinical interview the following statement is made by the clinician: ‘So you have been anxious since these changes occurred at your workplace.’ Which of the following interview technique best describes the above statement?","options":{"A":"Facilitation","B":"Open-ended question","C":"Closed-ended question","D":"Interpretation","E":"Reflecting"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Reflections are statements where the psychiatrist repeats what the patient has just said. This gives an opportunity to correct one’s understanding of what the patient said and to let the patient know that the clinician is listening and trying to understand the situation the patient is in."},{"question":"Which of the following interview techniques is least directive?","options":{"A":"Limit setting","B":"Summarizing","C":"Re-direction","D":"Repetitive questioning","E":"Narrow-focused questions"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Directiveness in the interview ensures that a clinician has all the information needed from a patient. Highly directive intervention aims to focus and restrict the patient’s speech content and behaviour. These may include check lists or yes/no questions. Limit setting and redirection include situations where a clinician attempts to change the direction of the interview, especially when the interview is not progressing in the detail of information transferred."},{"question":"Which of the following is a supportive intervention during a clinical interview process?","options":{"A":"Open-ended questions","B":"Acknowledgment of affect","C":"Confrontation","D":"Taking a medical history","E":"Summarization"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Being empathetic and acknowledging a patient’s emotional state helps in facilitating progression of clinical interview. These are supportive interventions required in various degrees by patients. Summarization is not an intervention but a technique facilitating a clinician’s understanding of a patient’s story. Confrontation may be helpful in some situations, but it cannot be considered as a supportive intervention during clinical interview."},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true when inquiring about suicidal ideation?","options":{"A":"This should not be asked unless the patient volunteers information","B":"Asking about suicidal ideation can instill suicidal ideas in a person","C":"A person who intends to attempt suicide will never divulge","D":"Passive suicidal ideas must be inquired further for any plans made","E":"The aim of the assessment is to corner the patient into a disclosure"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Thoughts of self harm should always be inquired about. Contemplation of suicide is very common among the mentally ill. There is no evidence that inquiring about suicidal ideations increases the risk of committing suicide. In fact many patients would welcome an opportunity to discuss any suicidal thoughts with a professional."},{"question":"‘Do you ever hear voices commenting on what you are doing?’ This question is usually asked to ascertain the presence of which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Bleuler’s primary symptoms","B":"Schneider’s first-rank symptoms","C":"Command hallucinations","D":"Catatonic symptoms of schizophrenia","E":"Negative symptoms of schizophrenia"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"First rank symptoms (FRS), proposed by Kurt Schneider, suggest a diagnosis of schizophrenia. These symptoms are not specific for schizophrenia. The prevalence of FRS in schizophrenia ranges from 28% to 72%. First rank symptoms do not carry any prognostic significance. The stated question in this case enquires for the presence of ‘running commentary’ hallucinations – voices commenting on patients’ thoughts or actions."},{"question":"Regarding the Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE), which of the following statements is true?","options":{"A":"The subject is asked to guess the answer if unsure","B":"If a person scores 3 on serial sevens, and scores 4 on spelling WORLD backwards then the score for attention is 3","C":"On the reading test one point is scored if the patient reads ‘Close your eyes’ out loud","D":"Education affects the rate of change of scores in normal and dementia subjects","E":"MMSE scores are not affected by socioeconomic status of a subject"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"While administering the MMSE, the subject is asked to guess the answer if he is unsure. This could possibly differentiate patients with pseudodementia who usually answer ‘I don’t know’ while truly demented patients often give wrong responses."},{"question":"Assessment of insight is an integral part of mental state examination in psychiatric practice. Regarding insight, which of the following statements is true?","options":{"A":"Patients with schizophrenia will never have insight into their illness","B":"OCD, being a neurosis, insight is always intact","C":"Intellectual insight is present when patients’ awareness and understanding of their symptoms lead to a change in behaviour","D":"Intellectual insight is the highest level of insight","E":"Loss of insight is similar to the concept of anosognosia in neurological illness"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The three dimensions of insight proposed by David include: the ability to label unusual experiences as pathological, to recognize that one has mental illness, and to comply with treatment."},{"question":"A patient with schizophrenia vividly describes how Martians are ‘reverse freezing’ earth to produce global warming. He stops to ask what you think about this. Choose the best response.","options":{"A":"This is a fantastic theory. But I want to know more about this. Tell me, have you ever seen these Martians?","B":"This seems possible but there is no proof for all this. Tell me, have you ever seen these Martians?","C":"This cannot be true. Martians do not exist. Tell me, have you ever seen these Martians?","D":"Tell me, have you ever seen these Martians?","E":"What I think is not so important. I want to know more about what you think of this. Tell me, have you ever seen these Martians?"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Option A and B indicate collusion with the patient’s belief. Option C is a direct confrontation while D is evasion from the topic which can reduce engagement."},{"question":"Which one of the following is NOT an advisable first response when a patient discloses past sexual abuse at a clinical encounter?","options":{"A":"Postpone discussing the issue","B":"Ask if she wants to say anything more about this now","C":"Ask if she has ever disclosed this to anyone","D":"Ask if she sees a link between this and her current difficulties","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Childhood physical, sexual abuse, and neglect are extremely common experiences among those who develop serious mental health problems."},{"question":"Closed questions are best avoided in which of the following scenarios?","options":{"A":"A patient with suspected malingering","B":"A guarded patient not answering spontaneously","C":"A suggestible patient with learning difficulty","D":"A psychotic patient who is actively hallucinating","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"While interviewing people with limited intelligence, questions should be brief and worded in a simple way."},{"question":"Which of the following is the single best question to discern premorbid personality of a patient?","options":{"A":"How would you describe yourself?","B":"How would your friends describe you?","C":"What were you like before you became unwell?","D":"If we had met 10 years ago, what sort of person would I be talking to?","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"There is no single question that can reliably elicit premorbid personality traits."},{"question":"Which of the following is not a discriminating question to screen for harmful use of alcohol?","options":{"A":"Have you ever attempted to cut down your drinking?","B":"Do you get annoyed when people talk about your drinking?","C":"Have you ever felt guilty for drinking excessively?","D":"Do you drink every evening?","E":"Do you need a drink as soon as you wake up?"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The CAGE questionnaire includes questions on ‘Cut down’, ‘Annoyed’, ‘Guilty’, and ‘Eye opener’."},{"question":"A patient looks dishevelled, with unkempt hair and dirty, unwashed clothes. Self neglect is commonly noted in all of the following EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Alcoholism","B":"Chronic schizophrenia","C":"Depression","D":"Dementia","E":"Social phobia"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"While self neglect can be seen in any severe mental illness, it is not very common in isolated anxiety disorders."},{"question":"A 57-year-old lady with many previous hospitalizations is brought by police to casualty. She is wearing full make-up, green lipstick, shiny green nail polish, and green jewellery. She asks everyone at the admission unit to call her Ms Green. Which of the following diagnoses is most consistent with the above presentation?","options":{"A":"Mania","B":"Depression","C":"Panic attacks","D":"Obsessive compulsive disorder","E":"Learning disability"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Exuberant dressing and makeup suggests elevated mood."},{"question":"Which of the following domains of cognition is tested by administering Serial Sevens Test?","options":{"A":"Short-term memory","B":"Attention","C":"Language","D":"Registration","E":"Recall"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Serial sevens test is a part of Mini Mental State Examination."},{"question":"A 33-year-old man attending an out-patient clinic turns towards his left and spits out, muttering unintelligibly. He does this act at least three times in half an hour and appears very guarded. This gesture is suggestive of which of the following?","options":{"A":"Depression","B":"Suicidal thinking","C":"Low self esteem","D":"Responding to hallucination","E":"Acute confusion"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Hallucinatory behaviours, such as the one described in this example, are often noted in acutely psychotic patients with poor insight."},{"question":"A depressed patient does not smile or laugh when a joke is shared by a fellow patient. She shows a defect in which of the following aspects of mental state examination?","options":{"A":"Stability of affect","B":"Reactivity of affect","C":"Congruence of affect","D":"All of the above","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Reactivity of affect refers to change in affect in response to environmental cues."},{"question":"An elderly patient in a stroke ward laughs all of a sudden inappropriately, and within a few minutes becomes tearful and cries for no reason. She exhibits an abnormality in which of the following aspects of mental state examination?","options":{"A":"Stability of affect","B":"Reactivity of affect","C":"Congruence of affect","D":"All of the above","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Stability of affect refers to maintaining a particular affective state for a reasonable period of time."},{"question":"Which of the following is the major difference between mood and affect in mental state examination?","options":{"A":"Mood is short-lived while affect is longer lasting","B":"Mood is objective while affect is subjective","C":"Affect is transient but difficult to interpret","D":"Affect is transient and self reported","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Various schools of thought exist in distinguishing mood from affect."},{"question":"Nihilistic delusions will be congruent with which of the following findings of mental state examination?","options":{"A":"Depression","B":"Mania","C":"Depersonalization","D":"Grandiose delusion","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Nihilism is similar to pessimism with self reference of an extreme belief."},{"question":"When eliciting suicide risk, which of the following questions should be avoided if possible?","options":{"A":"Do you have any plans to kill yourself?","B":"How are you feeling in your mood?","C":"Have you ever considered life is not worth living?","D":"Have you ever wanted to go to sleep and never wake up?","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Direct questioning about suicidality does not increase risk of suicide."},{"question":"Which of the following is not a manifestation of hypothyroidism?","options":{"A":"Hypothermia","B":"Sparing of the posterior column sensations","C":"Dementia","D":"Cerebellar ataxia","E":"Loss of deep tendon reflexes"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Features suggestive of hypothyroidism include, slowing of EEG, excessive daytime sleepiness, hypothermia, cerebellar ataxia, dementia, psychosis."},{"question":"Russell’s sign is usually associated with which one of the following disorders?","options":{"A":"Schizophrenia","B":"Bipolar disorder","C":"Bulimia nervosa","D":"Panic disorder","E":"Somatization disorder"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Russell’s sign was first described in bulimia nervosa."},{"question":"On physical examination, you notice that a person with a history of substance misuse now has pilo-erection, dilated pupils, rhinorrhea, and he is yawning frequently. Withdrawal from which of the following substances can cause this presentation?","options":{"A":"Cocaine","B":"Opiate","C":"Cannabis","D":"Alcohol","E":"Amphetamine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"These features are suggestive of opiate withdrawal."},{"question":"A 50-year-old patient was brought to the A and E department in a confused state. On physical examination he has nystagmus, ocular palsy, and ataxia. Which of the following parts of clinical assessment is likely to be most relevant to this presentation?","options":{"A":"Past psychiatric history","B":"Assessment of insight","C":"Alcohol use history","D":"Developmental history","E":"Family history of dementia"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The features of acute confusion, nystagmus, ocular palsy, and ataxia are suggestive of Wernicke’s encephalopathy, possibly secondary to alcohol use in a 50-year-old male."},{"question":"An 18-year-old male, recently started on a medication, presents to the A&E department with slow, long-sustained, contorting, involuntary movements and postures involving proximal limb and axial muscles. Which of the following medications is most likely to cause the above presentation?","options":{"A":"Propranolol","B":"Diazepam","C":"Risperidone","D":"Procyclidine","E":"Sertraline"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The clinical situation given here is an example of an acute dystonic reaction in a young male, possibly a psychotic patient, who has been started on an antipsychotic."},{"question":"A 21-year-old female presented to the emergency department with complaints of recurrent attacks of severe dizziness, lasting for 10 to 20 minutes. On examination during the episode of dizziness, there was no evidence of nystagmus. Which one of the following is true?","options":{"A":"Her symptoms may be associated with fear of going to places from where escape is impossible","B":"Deafness is usually present","C":"Vertigo without nystagmus is suggestive of central vertigo of brainstem origin","D":"Antihistaminic medications are likely to be effective in this case","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Absence of nystagmus during an attack of dizziness almost always rules out vertigo secondary to labyrinthine or brain stem pathology."},{"question":"A sudden onset of chorea is least likely in which of the following conditions?","options":{"A":"Hyperthyroidism","B":"Hypoparathyroidism","C":"Pregnancy","D":"Hypernatremia","E":"Huntington’s disease"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The onset of Huntington’s disease is invariably insidious and gradually progressing."},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a feature of subacute combined degeneration of the spinal cord?","options":{"A":"Loss of pain and touch","B":"Sensory ataxia","C":"Loss of bladder tone","D":"Hyper-refl exia","E":"Absence of refl exes"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Features suggestive of subacute combined degeneration of the cord (SACD) include paraesthesias, difficulties with gait and balance, and signs of posterior column dysfunction."},{"question":"Which of the following physical symptoms is seen in factitious disorder?","options":{"A":"Unexplained bleeding","B":"Recurrent hypoglycaemia","C":"Grid iron abdomen","D":"Haemoptysis","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Factitious disorder is a condition where clinical symptoms are consciously and intentionally produced by the patient."},{"question":"A man admitted to the psychiatric intensive care unit with a manic episode, received 10 mg of haloperidol intramuscularly as he had turned violent. He became unresponsive shortly afterwards. On examination, there is evidence of confusion, labile BP, hyperthermia, rigidity, and dysphagia. What is the most important differential diagnosis?","options":{"A":"Acute dystonia","B":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome","C":"Tardive dyskinesia","D":"Akathisia","E":"Parkinsonism"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome is a medical emergency that can occur when treating a patient with antipsychotics."},{"question":"Which of the following questionnaires is used to identify psychiatric ‘caseness’ in the general population?","options":{"A":"MMPI","B":"HDRS","C":"GHQ","D":"YMRS","E":"Repertory Grid"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"General health questionnaire (GHQ) is used to define psychiatric ‘caseness’ in epidemiological studies."},{"question":"Characteristic feature of Argyll Robertson pupil include all of the following EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Light near dissociation","B":"Irregular pupil","C":"Miosis","D":"Iris atrophy","E":"Flynn phenomenon"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Argyll Robertson pupil (ARP) is characteristically associated with neurosyphilis."},{"question":"Thunderclap headache is highly suggestive of which one of the following?","options":{"A":"Subarachnoid haemorrhage","B":"Migraine","C":"Cluster headache","D":"Temporal arteritis","E":"Tension headache"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Thunderclap headaches are sudden onset, severe headaches radiating behind the occiput with some degree of associated neck stiffness."},{"question":"Waddling gait is characteristic of which of the following neurological difficulties?","options":{"A":"Proximal muscle weakness","B":"Hemiplegia","C":"Cerebellar lesions","D":"Sensory ataxia","E":"Astasia abasia"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Waddling gait is seen with severe proximal muscle weakness."},{"question":"A 59-year-old man has a small, spastic tongue with significant difficulty in pronouncing consonants. On neurological examination, he has a brisk jaw jerk. Which of the following is the most likely explanation for the above presentation?","options":{"A":"Bulbar palsy","B":"Pseudobulbar palsy","C":"Myasthenia gravis","D":"Extrapyramidal dysarthria","E":"Dysphonia"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Bilateral upper motor neurone lesions of the corticobulbar tract result in pseudobulbar or spastic dysarthria."},{"question":"When mimicking the use of a screwdriver a patient rotates his arm at the shoulder but fixes his elbow. Which of the following could be diagnosed with the above presentation?","options":{"A":"Ideational apraxia","B":"Ideomotor apraxia","C":"Limb kinetic apraxia","D":"Conduction apraxia","E":"Conceptual apraxia"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Apraxia is defined as the inability to carry out a motor act despite the absence of sensory or motor deficits."},{"question":"A patient is asked to prepare a sandwich in order to test her ability to perform a sequence of acts. This test is aimed at demonstrating which of the following?","options":{"A":"Ideational apraxia","B":"Ideomotor apraxia","C":"Limb kinetic apraxia","D":"Conduction apraxia","E":"Conceptual apraxia"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Ideational apraxia is an inability to correctly sequence a series of goal-directed acts in spite of the ability to execute the instructions when broken down into single acts."},{"question":"Syndrome of isolated loss of auditory comprehension and repetition, without any abnormality of speech, naming, reading, or writing is suggestive of which of the following?","options":{"A":"Pure word deafness","B":"Wernicke’s aphasia","C":"Broca’s aphasia","D":"Anomic aphasia","E":"Transcortical aphasia"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Pure word deafness is a syndrome of isolated loss of auditory comprehension and repetition, without any abnormality of speech, naming, reading, or writing."},{"question":"A well-educated solicitor develops a sudden cerebrovascular deficit which results in loss of ability to read or write, though he is able to speak reasonably well. The dysfunction produced by the ischaemia is called","options":{"A":"Alexia with agraphia","B":"Alexia without agraphia","C":"Transcortical aphasias","D":"Global aphasia","E":"Wernicke’s aphasia"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Alexia is the acquired inability to read. Alexia with agraphia is seen in angular gyrus lesions and is associated with Gerstmann syndrome."},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a feature of upper motor neurone lesion?","options":{"A":"Hyper-refl exia","B":"Hypertonia","C":"Loss of voluntary movement","D":"Normal muscle bulk","E":"Fasciculations"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Muscle atrophy, fasciculations, absent reflexes, and hypotonia are features suggestive of lower motor neurone lesion."},{"question":"A 65-year-old patient has been drinking nearly 80 units of alcohol a week for the last 13 years. He has numerous physical complications of alcohol use including cirrhosis and cerebellar degeneration. Which of the following is NOT a feature of cerebellar dysfunction?","options":{"A":"Positive Romberg’s sign","B":"Positive finger nose test","C":"Positive heel shin test","D":"Dysdiadochokinesia","E":"Pendular knee jerk"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Cerebellar limb ataxia is characterized by dysmetria (past pointing), intention tremor, dysdiadochokinesia, and excessive rebound of outstretched arms against a resistance that is suddenly removed."},{"question":"In a road traffic accident, a 34-year-old man sustains crush injury of the spine. One half of his spinal cord is damaged severely at the level of the tenth thoracic vertebra. Which of the following is a feature of hemisection of the spinal cord?","options":{"A":"Contralateral weakness","B":"Contralateral loss of pain sensation","C":"Contralateral loss of proprioception","D":"Ipsilateral loss of temperature sensation","E":"The sensory level is at the same level as the lesion (T10)"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Brown–Sequard syndrome is the result of hemisection of the spinal cord."},{"question":"A patient presents in an agitated state with increased sweating and tremors. On examination she has signs of Grave’s disease. Which is the commonest sign noted in thyroid ophthalmopathy?","options":{"A":"Lid lag","B":"Lid retraction","C":"Compressive optic neuropathy","D":"Diplopia","E":"Conjunctival congestion"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Lid retraction is the most common clinical feature of Grave’s ophthalmopathy."},{"question":"Headache associated with ipsilateral nasal congestion, rhinorrhea, lacrimation, redness of the eye is characteristic of which of the following?","options":{"A":"Classical migraine","B":"Tension headache","C":"Cluster headache","D":"Headache secondary to depression","E":"Temporal arteritis"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Cluster headache is considered as a vascular headache syndrome."},{"question":"Epilepsy associated with learning disability, shagreen patches, and ash leaf macules are seen in which of the following?","options":{"A":"Epidermal nevus syndrome","B":"Tuberous sclerosis","C":"Neurofibromatosis","D":"Sturge–Weber syndrome","E":"Fabry’s disease"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Tuberous sclerosis is a congenital disease where hyperplasia of ectodermal and mesodermal cells leads to various lesions in the skin, nervous system, heart, kidney and other organs."},{"question":"Parkinsonian features associated with downward gaze palsy and pseudobulbar dysarthria is characteristic of which of the following conditions?","options":{"A":"Multisystem atrophy","B":"Idiopathic Parkinson’s disease","C":"Drug-induced parkinsonism","D":"Progressive supranuclear palsy","E":"Corticobasal degeneration"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Progressive supranuclear palsy is a degenerative neurological disease with parkinsonian symptoms as a prominent clinical feature."},{"question":"All of the following conditions that affect the trigeminal nerve present with significant sensory loss EXCEPT","options":{"A":"Multiple sclerosis","B":"Trigeminal neuralgia","C":"Acoustic neuroma","D":"Meningioma","E":"Neurofibroma"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Trigeminal neuralgia is characterized by episodic shooting pain in facial areas supplied by trigeminal nerve."},{"question":"Which of the following is a cause of bilateral facial nerve palsy?","options":{"A":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","B":"Sarcoidosis","C":"Guillain–Barré syndrome","D":"Wernicke–Korsakoff syndrome","E":"All of the above"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Causes of bilateral facial palsy include granulomatous and connective tissue diseases such as systemic lupus erythematosus, Sjögren’s syndrome, sarcoidosis."},{"question":"A patient known to have bipolar illness is on lithium. Which of the following will prompt you to check his lithium levels?","options":{"A":"Delayed ankle jerk","B":"Rising serum creatinine","C":"Dysarthria","D":"Fine tremor","E":"Alopecia"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Lithium toxicity results in two major groups of symptoms – neurological and gastrointestinal."},{"question":"Which one of the following is a physical sign noted in anorexia nervosa?","options":{"A":"Lanugo hair","B":"Grey hair","C":"Brown hair","D":"Alopecia areata","E":"Thickened, coarse hair"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Lanugo hair is thin, infantile hair noted on the torso and limbs of severely anorexic patient."},{"question":"Sleep spindles and K complexes on electroencephalogram (EEG) are seen in which of the following phase of sleep?","options":{"A":"REM phase","B":"Stage 1 NREM phase","C":"Stage 2 NREM phase","D":"Stage 3 NREM phase","E":"Stage 4 NREM phase"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"During sleep, the body goes through two types of physiological states. This has been divided into REM and NREM phase according to EEG studies."},{"question":"Electroencephalogram (EEG) is a commonly used diagnostic test. Which of the following statements regarding EEG is NOT correct?","options":{"A":"EEG signals are generated by the cerebral cortex","B":"EEG depends on afferent inputs from subcortical structures, including the thalamus and brainstem reticular formation","C":"Alpha rhythm and sleep spindles are produced by thalamic activity","D":"Diagnostic EEG does not routinely record the activity of inferior temporal cortex","E":"EEG changes are often very specific to a disease"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"An electroencephalograph represents cerebral cortical activity."},{"question":"A 32-year-old school teacher is admitted for constipation and acute abdominal pain. She experiences visual and tactile hallucinations with intense anxiety. She develops motor weakness of her legs on administration of hypnotics and diclofenac. Which of the following laboratory tests is indicated?","options":{"A":"Serum lipid levels","B":"Serum folate","C":"Urine glucose","D":"Urine porphyrins","E":"Serum ceruloplasmin"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"This scenario depicts acute intermittent porphyria (AIP)."},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT helpful in differentiating pseudoseizures from true epileptic seizures?","options":{"A":"Asymmetric movements of limbs and side-to-side movement of the head during ictal activity","B":"Raised postictal prolactin levels","C":"Ictal EEG","D":"Long-lasting seizures that wax and wane over time","E":"Having an established diagnosis of epilepsy in the past"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"All of these features except a history of seizure disorder may help to differentiate seizures from pseudoseizures."},{"question":"Clozapine is strongly associated with fatal agranulocytosis. Which of the following is true regarding clozapine-induced agranulocytosis?","options":{"A":"The risk of agranulocytosis is greatest in the first year","B":"Patients must have weekly blood tests throughout clozapine treatment","C":"After a year blood tests can be discontinued","D":"An amber report from the monitoring body indicates that clozapine should be stopped immediately","E":"A red alert indicates that clozapine could be restarted in a patient who previously had an amber report"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Incidence of agranulocytosis in patients on clozapine is less than 1 per 100 patients."},{"question":"Which one of the following statements regarding the dexamethasone suppression test is FALSE?","options":{"A":"Healthy subjects show cortisol suppression on dexamethasone administration","B":"Depressed patients show more cortisol suppression than normal controls","C":"The test has a specificity around 25% to 40% for diagnosing depression","D":"Patients with a positive test may respond better to ECT than those with a negative test","E":"Dexamethasone suppression is not routinely used as a clinical test for depression"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Exogenous administration of the steroid dexamethasone usually inhibits endogenous cortisol secretion."},{"question":"Which of the following is an advantage of using CT scan over MRI scan for diagnostic purposes?","options":{"A":"Finer details are seen easily with CT scan","B":"Absence of radiation exposure in CT scan","C":"CT scan is more suitable in pregnant women","D":"CT scan is more immediately available in emergencies","E":"Anterior fossa is better visualized with CT scan"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Immediate availability, especially in head injury units, and ability to enable early detection of haemorrhages make CT scan the preferred diagnostic modality in emergency scenarios."},{"question":"Choose one of the following conditions where CT scan of brain is the investigation of choice","options":{"A":"Subarachnoid haemorrhage","B":"Demyelinating disease","C":"Meningeal neoplasm","D":"Viral meningitis","E":"Ischaemic infarction of cortex"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"MRI is more sensitive than CT for the detection of lesions of the spinal cord, cranial nerves, and posterior fossa structures."},{"question":"A patient with bipolar disorder recently stabilized on medications is brought to you with a history of fever for 4 days and blurred vision, muscle fasciculation, hyperactive tendon reflexes, and persistent nausea and vomiting for the last 2 days. Which one of the following may be implicated?","options":{"A":"Haloperidol","B":"Lithium","C":"Valproate","D":"Clonazepam","E":"Carbamazepine"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"In this case, a patient’s bipolar disorder has been stabilized on a particular medication."},{"question":"A patient who has chronic schizophrenia is on a depot antipsychotic medication. Your consultant asks for an ECG. Which of the following will be of most interest to him?","options":{"A":"PR interval","B":"RR interval","C":"U waves","D":"QT interval","E":"Axis of heart"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Prolonged QT interval can predispose to serious ventricular arrhythmia called torsades de pointes."},{"question":"Which of the following medications has the highest propensity to cause QT prolongation on ECG?","options":{"A":"Thioridazine","B":"Risperidone","C":"Quetiapine","D":"Haloperidol","E":"Olanzapine"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"ECG abnormalities occur in approximately 25% of all patients on antipsychotics."},{"question":"A patient who is on olanzapine for a long time is developing xanthoma. Which one of the following levels might be elevated in his blood?","options":{"A":"Creatinine","B":"Carotene","C":"Cholesterol","D":"Glucose","E":"Albumin"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Xanthomas indicate the presence of hyperlipidaemia."},{"question":"Which of the following nutrients, if deficient, can make treatment of depression difficult?","options":{"A":"B 12","B":"Riboflavin","C":"Nicotinamide","D":"Folate","E":"Magnesium"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Though folate deficiency itself is not a common cause of depression, in folate-deficient patients, supplementation might increase response to antidepressant treatment."},{"question":"Which of the following is a good predictor of metabolic side-effects of antipsychotics?","options":{"A":"QT interval","B":"Lipid levels","C":"HbA1c","D":"Waist circumference","E":"Ear lobe thickness"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Waist circumference is a better predictor than baseline weight with respect to metabolic syndrome."},{"question":"In patients with suspected dementia, which of the following neuroimaging modalities is clinically helpful to differentiate dementia of Lewy body type from Alzheimer’s dementia?","options":{"A":"CT scan","B":"Structural MRI scan","C":"Functional MRI scan","D":"Dopamine transporter SPECT scan","E":"PET scan"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"DAT (dopamine transporter) scan is a SPECT scan that visualizes dopamine transporter."},{"question":"Which of the following EEG rhythms has the highest frequency?","options":{"A":"Beta","B":"Theta","C":"Alpha","D":"Delta","E":"Mu"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Beta >13 Hz, Alpha 8 to 13 Hz, Theta 4 to 7Hz, Delta < 3Hz."},{"question":"In patients with delirium due to hepatic failure which of the following EEG change may be seen?","options":{"A":"Hypsarrythmia","B":"Spike and wave pattern","C":"Periodic complexes","D":"Sleep spindles","E":"Slow triphasic waves"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Slow triphasic waves are typically seen in metabolic encephalopathies such as hepatic failure."},{"question":"Which of the following suggests a successful seizure activity after ECT?","options":{"A":"Ictal facilitation","B":"Postictal suppression","C":"Ictal suppression","D":"Dominant alpha waves","E":"See-saw pattern"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"EEG during ECT treatment shows sharp waves and spikes during the seizure."},{"question":"In neurological examination, which of the following is seen in hypothyroidism?","options":{"A":"Hypertonia","B":"Loss of deep tendon reflexes","C":"Slow and sluggish deep tendon reflexes","D":"Clonus on testing deep tendon reflexes","E":"Exaggerated jaw jerk"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"A characteristic neurological feature associated with hypothyroidism is delayed relaxation of deep tendon reflexes."},{"question":"Which one of the following patients is not suitable for undergoing MRI investigation when required?","options":{"A":"A 32-year-old woman with last menstrual period 3 months ago","B":"A 74-year-old man with suspected Lewy body dementia","C":"A 53-year-old man with a cardiac pacemaker inserted 10 years ago","D":"A 44-year-old lady with a family history of haemochromatosis","E":"A 22-year-old man with epilepsy and mild learning disability"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Insertion of cardiac pacemaker precludes MRI study as the magnetic field can disturb the pacemaker rhythm."},{"question":"Which of the following is the most clinically useful method of diagnosing Alzheimer’s disease?","options":{"A":"Clinical interview","B":"CT scans","C":"Functional MRI","D":"SPECT","E":"Lumbar puncture"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Various guidelines exist for diagnosing dementia. Most of them endorse routinely using clinical interview for making a diagnosis of dementia."}]');export{e as default};
